Welcome to The Test Set. Here we talk with some of the brightest thinkers and tinkerers
in statistical analysis, scientific computing, and machine learning. Digging into what makes
them tick, plus the insights, experiments, and OMG moments that shape the field.
In this episode we talk with Trevor Manz. Trevor started out in chemistry and computational
biology, before moving into visualization research, where he ran into a problem. Researchers
could build these sophisticated tools, but getting them into the hands of people analyzing
data was another story. That frustration eventually led him towards Python notebooks, and to creating
AnyWidget, which makes it easier to build interactive tools that work across the computational
notebook ecosystem. Today he's a founding engineer at Marimo, where he's pushing that
idea in a new direction. If notebooks are such a useful place for humans to explore
data, could they also be a better place for AI agents to do it? And what would AI agents
need to use notebooks effectively? We're joined by self-proclaimed notebook skeptic
Hadley Wickham, which I think makes for a fun discussion. So with that, Trevor Manz.
Trevor, welcome to The Test Set. So you're Trevor Manz, scientist, programmer, and as
you say, Wisconsinite, which I'm excited to dig into. You created AnyWidget and you're
a founding engineer at Marimo. Yeah. Thanks so much for coming on. So happy to have you.
Yeah. Thanks so much for having me.
And by way of introduction, I guess I'm, I'm Michael Chow, the host of The Test Set, and
this is Hadley Wickham, co-host and chief scientist at Fawcett. Yeah, sure. I'm so excited.
I know you've been doing a lot with Marimo and notebooks, and especially with Marimo
pair. I'm, I think, yeah, I'm so curious to talk a bit more about Marimo and notebooks.
Maybe just to kick it off, you could explain a little bit about what Marimo is and kind
of like who uses it and what, what excites you about it?
Yeah. So Marimo, Marimo is like a new kind of...
Marimo, I'm so sorry. Yeah.
So Marimo is a new kind of Python notebook and I like to describe them as a delightful
reactive Python notebook. And the first piece is that we're a delightful notebook insofar
as that we've been able to look a lot at how notebooks are used in practice and then really
think about creating a very built-in user experience for many different ways that notebooks
are used, like traditional notebooks are being used. And then the second piece there is that
we are a reactive notebook. So similar to observable notebooks or Pluto, which are sort
of from the Julia ecosystem, Marimo does not... Marimo understands the relationships between
your cells, not based off of the ordering that you wrote the cells, but the actual data
flow. So where your variables are declared and how they're used to find the execution
order of your notebook. And that leads to eliminating this kind of hidden state that
can come from having sort of a traditional Python REPL or like a traditional Python notebook.
And then the third piece is that we are a Python notebook. So we're like only focused
on Python. And that is all the way from a lot of the user interfaces oriented around
data structures that are in the Python ecosystem. We have things like a built-in package manager.
So for when you're trying to work on your data, we can sell packages for you. All the
way down to the file format itself is not like a JSON file. It's actually a Python script.
So yeah, those are the three things I think that sort of characterize Marimo in contrast
to other sort of computational notebooks.
Yeah. So, and I appreciate you helping with the pronunciation. I feel like this also came
up at PyCon when I saw y'all that this is the perfect chance that I'm going to work
Marimo in and Marimo out forever. So I'm glad that we have this to practice.
But happy to help out there.
It's interesting to hear too, you mentioned like as a package manager and some of that,
like maybe the surprising scope of things that kind of enter in to a notebook. Like
if you want to be delightful and useful, that even it sounds like package management kind
of becomes an important piece.
So we like to say that Marimo is like, you know, we're an open source computational notebook
that's used across like industry research and education. And then beyond that, I think
as well from being able to look at the different ways that people are trying to use traditional
notebooks, we've also thought a lot about, you know, you build up a notebook, but like
what are the directions that you might want to take it? So some notebooks look more like
doing like data pipelines and those you can run as Python scripts and maybe have very
few visual elements. There's some that maybe are more in this, you know, world of like
literate programming where it's both like your code, your code is very forward. And
then you have pros explaining and contextualizing the code. And then we have, you know, because
we're a reactive Python notebook, the cells can react to user interactions. And so there's
a mode within Marimo that we call like app mode that you can just hide all of your code
and then you just have the outputs. And so for that set of users, it's more like presentational
or, you know, showing people almost these like data apps, but without having to show
the code. And I think that's, so it's quite hard to like generalize like what that user
group is. But I think if I could generalize it, it would be, you know, individuals that
are not professional software engineers, but like have traditionally learned a little bit
of code to do some thing with data.
And do you think, is it like mostly like data people broadly construed or are there people
doing like non-data stuff? I'm sure there are people doing non-data stuff, but is that
like a user base you think about?
Yeah, I guess one thing I've noticed by introducing like a reactive experience to an ecosystem
like Python, we do have users that are, you know, trying to build, like they've sort of
maybe learned a little bit of Python in their education and now they have sort of a toolkit
or that background with that coding language and now a toolkit that allows them to make
like programs a bit more interactive. So we do see things like games, I guess, being built
inside of Marimo. But I'd say in terms of like the scope of where we are taking the
project, it's definitely oriented around, you know, generally folks have some unstructured
data, they're going to like load it into memory and like, yeah, do something with that
data. Either that be, you know, perform some kind of analysis or maybe do some sort of
like presentational scaffold into like an application.
I guess like more, sorry, more concrete, just to remind me of like, do you know processing?
It was like an art, really like a framework for doing kind of art explorations. And it
feels like you could definitely drive a reactive notebook in that direction as well for doing
computational art. That would be a cool application.
Yeah, we definitely have a community member, I'm forgetting his name. I can share a link,
but he's a mathematics teacher who has all these really cool generative like art displays
that he would normally, I think, historically in the past would write these like really
these scripts in Matplotlib that, you know, demonstrate some sort of like a lot with like
fractals and now like being able to grab that plotting library, add a slider and now you
can like play around with that fractal.
Yeah, so we definitely have like art that's being generated, but often to like demonstrate
something, some sort of like mathematical concept or something that is sort of, I guess,
like coming from more like the education side.
I think hearing your response, maybe think that, you know, surprisingly, a lot of problems
are data problems, you know, whether it's like music or art or different things. So I
could say I wouldn't be surprised if Mirambo is used in kinds of all kinds of use cases
that aren't like a data scientist analyze crunching numbers like for their company.
I will say I love the app mode.
I feel like app mode is really killer to be able to go from a notebook where you're
analyzing to this kind of like display more dash 40 setup has been super cool.
And that that kind of made me think of one question.
Hadley, do you use much notebooks?
I know like in R it's a bit less common.
I'd be curious maybe just for context to hear some of your experience.
I think like I've never really gotten notebooks and I kind of feel like there's this.
Like when you start learning, like you either learn a tool like R with like a ripple and
you learn something like R Markdown or Korto where you like kind of render a document or
you go down the notebook path where it's kind of like intermixed things that you run and
text and it feels like once you go down one of those paths, like the other path just feels
like weird and unnatural and like it's not like obviously like people can be successful
on either path.
But I don't know if I've met anyone who's like, oh, yeah, like I really like R Markdown
and I really like notebooks and somehow I've like synthesized them in my head.
So, yeah, so like when I yeah, like I played a bit with Marimo and I just felt like really
strange, especially the especially the fact that the the order of the chunks in the
document does not matter.
Like it's only the order of dependencies between them, which that did feel a lot more
like this literate programming, which to be honest, I mostly have like negative feelings
about based on LaTeX documentation manuals for LaTeX packages, which have either of you
used LaTeX?
Oh, not for so long.
Yeah.
I think like the documentation packages for LaTeX and because I've written this literate
programming, so which explains how the whole thing works and you're like like there's now
a 400 page PDF that explains how this tool works and you're like, I don't care.
I just want to know which option do I need to set to do the thing that I want.
So I was like, I don't know, I felt like I got burned by literate programming on LaTeX
package documentation.
Yeah, I would say like the the extension of or having like the like having reactivity and
that the cell order does not matter, like introduces its own set of like new sort of
tradeoffs and problems.
But but those have been things that we've tried to address more through like having
different debugging tools inside of the notebooks.
If you're like focusing on a cell, we have this thing like actually inspired from
Observable that's like a mini map that allows you to sort of jump around and trace back
to like where like the dependencies of that cells are.
So you can kind of like focus locally, I guess, on like the step of your analysis that
you're working on.
But there certainly are tradeoffs to having, yeah, like an environment, you know, a
document that you can read top down.
We don't we don't force you to move around your cells.
So you could write your notebooks in that way.
But we also think that it provides this freedom for when you want to do something in
maybe take your notebook in a direction that's more like an app mode.
Now you can move around those cells and you haven't had to like switch tools.
I think prior to working on a reactive Python notebook, when I had some sort of like data
task and I didn't want to make like a website and I didn't want to do like a script and
maybe it was going to be like presentational prior to like starting on that problem, I'd
have to choose like think about the tool that I would want to use to like start that.
So it'd be like, oh, maybe this will be a Streamlit app or maybe this will be a Jupyter
notebook or I'm going to start working on this library and I'm going to like prototype
that in a notebook. But as I'm working in a Jupyter notebook, I started to get this
itch where I'm like, I got to move this code out of this notebook because like I'm not
going to be able to like use this from other files.
And I think Marimba provides a really nice on-ramp for like starting with data problems
and then a lot of different off-ramps, depending on like what direction you want to take those.
Yeah, what direction you want to take the work that you've done inside that notebook
and that's sort of like package it up for someone else.
I guess what one thing Hadley said that.
You all reminded me of is that.
I guess our users do have the problem, Trevor, you mentioned like having to switch or choose
the right thing for your problem, like I have noticed one thing I've.
Because I've demoed Marimo, oh Marimo.
All right, we got this two people at the company because I'm a huge Marimo fan and.
It is funny, like our users, sometimes there's this funny switch of like you're analyzing
data, so you're using a tool like R Markdown or you're you're producing plots, but then
when you want to dashboard, you kind of have to like copy your code into a dashboarding
tool like Shiny.
And so there's kind of this funny moment, like when will I turn that dashboard knob?
And I feel like Marimo, one thing that it has been really nice is it's the same thing,
like you're in the notebook, you can interact with the data, you can plot it, but then you
could switch to app mode and actually now it is like a reactive dashboard.
Yeah, it's a really interesting framing because I think we have tried to do that at various
points, like through R Markdown, like you can do dashboards in R Markdown and we
experimented with a way of doing like Shiny apps inside R Markdown, but they just never
really felt quite right.
Like it's an interesting tradeoff because it's.
Like there is something like it's it's nice to be able to like not have to decide what
the final output is going to be at the beginning, but it is sometimes like sometimes your
final output like shapes the way you think about the problem so much that you do want
to like kind of commit to something upfront, which I mean, obviously you can do that with
Marimo, like it's not like you can't commit to one thing, but it's just that's an
interesting. It's an interesting problem to tackle.
Yeah, and I think, I mean, again, they're like certainly tradeoffs as well of like
deferring that choice like upfront, like because of what you said in terms of the way
that, you know, your tools and approaches like shape the way that you think about the
problem. But I think what I found increasingly was, you know, I'm biased because I
started working at Marimo, but like prior to that even was that a lot more problems
felt like well suited for a notebook compared to like what I'd been using them for
before. And so I find a lot more things now where I'm like, oh, that could just be a
notebook and maybe one day I'll come back to it and start and pick up where I left off
there. And it could be a hybrid of like almost like an app or like, you know, I work on
this project called AnyWidget. There could be like an AnyWidget that I've thrown in
there that I'm playing around with some data and it doesn't have to be like stringing
together a lot of different files or projects.
And it can kind of just all like live in this like this thing that resembles something
closer to like traditional software than like a notebook, but isn't also not like a
proper like program or it isn't, you know, just a clean Python module.
Like it has like this runtime and everything as well.
So I mean, I think one thing we should say like to be explicit is like like traditional
Jupyter notebooks are like a JSON file, whereas Marimo notebooks are just a Python
file with some like special annotations.
Right. So you can just you can just execute them like a regular like they're an
executable thing, not like this weird kind of like mix of a bunch of different things,
which makes them like very different to traditional notebooks.
I'm actually so curious to hear a bit, maybe going back to your, maybe to take a step
back and go to your like journey into Marimo.
And I don't know if being a Wisconsinite has something to do with it, but I actually
like, I was so curious because I noticed you mentioned you're like from Wisconsin.
As I understand, you went to Kenyon College in Ohio.
And then you jumped to Cambridge in the UK and then back to the other Cambridge in the
U.S. to do a PhD at Harvard.
I'm so curious to hear a little bit about your like the places you've been and in some
of that, because you've been so many different places, starting with Wisconsin.
Tell us a little bit about the places you've been and and how you've liked them.
Yeah, OK. Yeah.
So I mean, I'm yeah, I grew up in the Midwest.
I'm from Eau Claire, Wisconsin, a small-ish town.
Like it's now I feel like as I'm zooming in on a map or if I'm flying over Wisconsin,
you'll like see Eau Claire now.
So we're big enough that like that, like it'll be one of the few, the few cities that
like pop ups. But it felt very small, like growing up there.
And then I went to like Kenyon College was in Ohio.
It's like very small liberal arts college where I studied chemistry and I swam
competitively. So I was like definitely in like the natural sciences, but did not
really work with computers that much.
I mean, I use computers.
I made websites for fun, but I didn't for my own like research.
I was very much in a wet lab doing like organic synthesis.
So it was it felt very distant from the type of work that I end up doing for my
research.
Oh, is there a lot around it, like in Kenyon College?
Yeah. So Kenyon College, it's in, it's about an hour outside of Columbus, Ohio.
So there are about 2,000 students.
Yeah, being a liberal arts college, like I got a bachelor of arts in chemistry, so I
studied like humanities and things outside of like the natural sciences as well.
And I think it was just a really nice place to have faculty that were like very hands
on with like learning.
So like, you know, in contrast to going to some of the places where I ended up for
graduate school, like the priority at that university or at Kenyon College was like
having faculty that were very like engaged and like trying to get folks into
research. So I had, I think it was my academic advisor had a lab and he was like,
hey, if you want to like do some research, you should you should try it out.
And I didn't, it sounded interesting.
So that's sort of where I started my research career, I guess.
Yeah. And then from there you went to Cambridge, is that right?
Yeah, I tell you, it was like a bit of a journey, I guess, like because it was such a
small school, I would like apply for various like summer research internships.
And I ended up taking like an internship in St.
Louis, Missouri at the Danforth Plant Science Center.
And I was doing a lot of like wet lab kind of like molecular biology stuff.
But they ran this workshop with computer vision.
And I was like the first time that I used like I think it was a Python program called
like OpenCV. They gave us like a Raspberry Pi.
And I remember I was like that summer I was imaging a lot of like Arabidopsis, which
is this model organism.
And I was measuring all the apertures by hand.
And then like we ran this like computer vision program that like I saw like kind of
automate a lot of that.
And I think it was like kind of this like revelation of like, oh, my gosh, I think I
should figure out how to use this stuff.
But also it was like kind of interesting because we like it was a very visual like
output, like you could kind of see where it measured things on the actual images and
being able to like as a human, like look and observe that you could kind of see where
the algorithms would like fail, being able to actually like highlight a region.
And so I think that's I mean, in retrospect, it's easy to like construct some
narrative of when I started down this path into like visualization.
But like that was probably somewhere we're having the somewhat like web background and
like also this like science background and seeing like how the ways that, you know,
visualizations can sort of surprise you or like confirm like some something that you
suspected in the data.
It became kind of this interest of mine to see like, yeah, if you know, if I am
applying algorithms or using computers to like assist my under help myself automate
some of this stuff that was really tedious, like, are there ways that I can bring myself
in the loop to make sure I'm like pretty confident about like the application of
those tools?
Had you done a lot of computer programming up to that point?
Not really. Yeah, I mostly like web, HTML, CSS, JavaScript kind of stuff.
And then after that summer, I think when I went back to doing more research, I got I
started like trying to use actually R was the first programming language I like really
sat down with to learn for data analysis.
Never heard of it. Yeah, yeah, yeah.
And and then I think I just got really interested in, yeah, like software generally
for like for doing data analysis.
And that sort of led to, I guess, not really like a total pivot, but switching into like
looking more into doing like computational research rather than like sitting under the
hood with a pipette was sort of the direction that things went.
And then from there, you went to Cambridge to do a master's.
Were you, yeah, were you thinking of going like the academic route or kind of where
were you at that point?
Yeah, I think at that point I was interested in doing.
A PhD, maybe at some point, but I, I had, but because because of my background, like
I really wanted to spend a little bit of time, like doing some software stuff there,
like, like data or spending time improving my maths and sort of like becoming more of a
data person, maybe.
So that that was an interesting, yeah, like avenue, I guess it was sort of like a one
year master's.
And then after that, I joined into like a bioinformatics computational biology program
for the PhD.
How'd you like Cambridge?
Yeah, it was it was really interesting.
I mean, like coming from a very small liberal arts college and then also just being like
in the UK, like there are a lot of differences.
Also like a lot more European in terms of like the the population that was like at the
school and also in the program.
So that was, I mean, probably the best part of that experience was making a, we had a
very small cohort and just making like very close friends that now are sprinkled kind
of like throughout Europe.
But yeah, I think it was, it was a much different type of institution than like where I
went to undergrad.
So I think it also like taught me a lot about, you know, priorities in terms of research
or like like academic priorities for faculty at different universities.
There's something interesting about, I feel like just all the places kind of you you
bounce between.
It seems like a big cut of both like American Midwest and like the UK.
So it's interesting to hear about.
I mean, I had to wear like a gown sometimes to like dinners at Cambridge, and that was
very like, I remember not even like thinking I didn't need like a suit or something.
And then I was really happy that I brought one because we oddly were wearing it a good
amount.
So that actually reminded me, like my dad did his PhD at Cornell and he had like this
part-time job, like checking that people were wearing their jackets to dinner.
He was like jacket police.
Is that?
Yeah.
Like the jacket bouncer.
And then I guess you mentioned, so you, you did your PhD at Harvard in the, what was the
lab called again?
Yeah, it's called the, we're called the High Dive Group now.
When I joined, the lead of the lab is Nils Gallenborg.
We rebranded at some point, I think to like, but we're like a visualization group.
So we, the way that the, the research that we worked on where we have a lot of close
collaborations with like experimental biologists in the department or outside of the
department at Harvard.
And then we kind of work with them to understand like their data problems and see if
like visualization, like yeah, visualizations could help or like really connect folks to
their data.
I think a nice thing with a field like biology is that a lot of the data are very
abstract.
So there, and like new types of experiments come out in which you like acquire and like
new information.
And so it's like kind of this nice, interesting pairing for folks that are really
interested in developing new visual representations because you have this really
abstract data type that you're trying to, you know, come up with new ways to represent
that are effective for helping understand information.
Yeah, I see.
So it's less, it might be less about tools necessarily, like rather than tools for
visualization, you could focus on like what visualizations would kind of like help people
work on these problems or like visualize the space well.
Yeah, I'd say like a pretty like classic example, example would be something like a
genome browser.
Like that's like a very, like the types of visual representations in a genome browser
are like well known, like it's a lot of bars and you know, like dots.
But then the type of data behind it and like the idea of like overlaying all these
different tracks and it being like zoomable and like panable and like also just laying
out the genome like linearly.
Like that's like a chosen representation for that information.
Although what I will say is like from the visualization community, like when I joined,
I was super excited about, you know, I'd gotten into working on, interested in
visualization.
Some of my first like open source contributions were in sort of like visualization
libraries.
And I think I was just motivated to have something that like kind of fit my background,
but where I could study visualization and work on it.
And it seemed like the focus of that community is really on these like novel
representations or because that is where like interesting, I don't know, like that's
kind of like where the field was.
And so the types of like applications that we, or the types of software that we would
work on would resemble like a lot more like monolithic like software applications.
Like it's, hey, we built this like viewer for this.
And what I found over time was that like we ran into all these practical barriers where
like that might make a really interesting like visualization paper, but like the field
is sort of interested in these like new representations, but things that were like are
kind of like boring to the field now, like still are not being used by like practitioners
that like have their hands on data.
And I think that that's where I really started to think like, or I took for granted
like the cost of the tools that we use.
Like if you are like, I use this tool and I work on my data every day and then I come
to you and I say, I made another tool for you.
It's like, okay, does that compliment my workflow?
Are you asking me to like throw out my previous thing?
Like, how do I get my data into that?
Like, these are all just questions that you start to have to either answer with software
in that application or like workflows to get data in there.
And I think I just got kind of frustrated in this feeling that we, the community that
felt like it had solutions.
And like, there was like kind of this disconnect back to like the folks that would
actually benefit from using them and in understanding their workflows in real ways.
I remember going to a Viz conference a while ago and having this just like really strong
feeling, like these people were like, this is like haute couture.
Like they're delivering, they're creating these amazing kind of bespoke pieces of art
that's tailored to one person.
And I was coming in and I'm like, I'm like a buyer at Target.
Like, if I can't get this on the back of a million people, like who cares?
Like, it's just such an interesting like difference in perspective.
But it just, it feels like that, like that, that.
— but it just feels like there's much more emphasis these days on actually shipping
stuff that people — more than the one research group you're carefully collaborating with
can use.
I think I started to think about it a lot more, too.
I think the reason why — it's not like that community set off to build these only specialized
applications, but in writing my PhD thesis in the end, I tried to think a lot about why
visualization software is kind of different from other software.
And I think a part of it is just that it touches so many pieces of the software stack, like
it has a backend, and it has the actual UI layer, so you can shell out to different commands
from a lot of different applications, but it's really hard to take this visual thing
that was built one way and stuff it in another one if they're built with totally different
technologies.
So yeah, I think I just started to focus — maybe there are ways that we could improve our software
practices in such a way that we could try to standardize a little bit more how we're
building these visual representations, such that we don't need to — one, we don't need
to build the all-encompassing tool that does everything, but maybe we can layer on just
the visualization layer into an environment where someone already knows what they're doing
with their data.
And that led me to looking at notebooks, because that was something that I used a lot for working
with data, and also our closest collaborators use Python notebooks.
And then yeah, also there's a way of extending Jupyter notebooks with something called Jupyter
Widgets, and that was sort of how I started playing around with this idea of taking web-based
visualizations and embedding them inside of the environment where people have their hands
on data rather than saying, hey, here's a new application, and sort of giving that feeling
of, hey, if there's this library, pip install it and get going, rather than like, oh, go
to this website, download the software, run this script to export into a particular file
format and then ingest it.
I mean, the other thing that did change is you could create — now you can create high-performance
visualizations in a web browser, and 10 years ago that required C++ code, or 20 years ago.
That is another — that's one of the reasons that it's so much easier today to distribute
this stuff.
Yeah.
That's fair.
I guess to the notebook point too, yeah, it's interesting because I — Trevor, you mentioned
like all of these applications had to worry about how does data come in?
And I guess if you look at it from the notebook side, it's like this kind of substrate can
handle that across everyone.
And it sounds like you're saying if you just focus on the visualization part, the notebook
can kind of take care of all these activities that every single bespoke app repeats, essentially?
Yeah.
The concrete example I like to give is like, imagine that you have an application that
like renders points, like a scatterplot application.
And someone's like, it's like, okay, how do I get my data into that?
It's like, okay, we take a CSV as input.
Okay, what are the columns of that CSV?
And then it's like, but what if I had a TSV or what if I had like a parquet file or like,
it starts to be that now that you're putting stress on that application to solve that layer
of like, how do I get my data into memory such that I can put it into this visual representation
versus in an environment like a notebook, you can kind of just say my data visualization
takes a data frame as input, and it should have these columns.
And then there's other libraries that someone is interested or that works in notebooks knows
how to get their data into a data frame.
And so you can really focus on like, the data types, like tabular versus maybe like multidimensional
arrays, or I feel like are kind of like the core data types in the data science ecosystem.
And then if we just build the visualization layers on top of that, you sort of reduce
the requirement of the front end of having to like understand or do that massaging of
the data.
And instead, you can sort of have a much like thinner, like actual visual representation
that you are contributing.
Yeah.
And then the bit that makes that work is you can now rely on the like, you can just expect
that the end user can like program so they can like stitch together the one package that
does import with another package does visualization, which again is, yeah, like has not always
been the case for visualization tools.
Yeah.
And I think like the same way that you could, you know, like the libraries like scikit-learn
don't necessarily import, or I don't actually know if they do, but like have IO primitives
in them.
It's more like algorithms that you apply to data structures.
And, you know, how do you do that for visualizations?
It's like, maybe we assume similar data structures, but we just do the visualization side and not
so much of like the pre-processing.
And in Marimo, just to tie it up with a bow too, in Marimo, this is a widget.
Is that right?
Yeah, exactly.
So, you know, to complete this, I guess, this thread with like Jupyter widgets, I started
working on them because they seem like this useful primitive for, you know, extending
notebooks with these interactive elements.
And just to be concrete, a widget is like a little bit of front end code.
So something that runs in your web browser that can embed directly into the output area
inside of a notebook.
So if you have a cell that runs some code, now you can have like some user defined front
end code that sits there.
But the really important bit is that also that code has a way of like communicating
back to your actual, where your Python objects live.
And so it provides this really rich interface for actually like, I can move a slider and
that changes the value that actually lives in Python, not just like in the front end,
like that state isn't trapped.
And so, yeah, Jupyter widgets are the mechanism by which Jupyter define like, here's how you
sort of coordinate these two worlds.
And what ended up happening was at the, you know, when widgets first came out, you had
this fragmentation of different front ends for Jupyter where you had like Google Colab
or VS Code or JupyterLab or even classic Jupyter.
And because the web browser didn't have like a standard module system, they all kind of
rolled their own system for like how you load third party JavaScript code.
And so what that meant was now every widget author like had to become an expert in like
web bundlers and package managers to be able to like create something that could be used
universally.
So I started working on a couple of Jupyter widgets.
I'd been working on building like, you know, web applications because that's how we built
a lot of the visualization tools.
It just felt like a lot different type of development.
Like it felt like it was like years before what I was familiar with, with kind of with
modern web development.
So AnyWidget, which is the project that came out of this, was originally just a way for
me to be able to iterate very quickly on like building like more of these and make it a
little bit more fun where I didn't have to like restart my browser and like refresh everything
to like see the updates.
It was trying to come up with unifying like the way that you wrote that front end code
more around how modern browsers talk today and then like ingesting that in a bunch of
different environments.
So I could sort of solve the platform compatibility problem once and then like just author this
thing that's a little bit more portable.
Just for some context too, I think people, like a lot of people think of AnyWidget today,
but yeah, having lived through the shift to AnyWidget, yeah, I can't overstate how convenient
it is to have something run across all these different platforms that I do feel like that
juggling was real of figuring out like I can run in the Jupyter notebook.
Now I've done the work to figure it out for Google Colab, but like to have it in one place
and not even have to worry about that is so convenient, seems like.
Yeah.
And I think also like, you know, when I've used notebooks for prototyping like Python
code, like maybe to speak more concretely, like I use notebooks to prototype code because
it's a way that I can run little snippets of code and try them out.
But in order previously to like even just experiment with the idea of like a visual
output, like a widget, like you'd have to like create a new Python project and like
kind of like link and like start this like build process in Bundler.
And so like you couldn't just like play around with, hey, maybe it'd be fun to like draw
these things in the web and put them there.
And that was probably the most like exciting thing to me originally with AnyWidget was
just the fact that inside of a notebook, I could like start playing with both front
end and my Python code together and then kind of get these proof of concepts very quickly
without having to like start a whole new project.
So does Marimo like extend the Jupyter widget protocol in some way, or is it just much better
because it's not reactive?
So when one widget changes, the others can update automatically.
Yeah, that's a great question.
So part of this is that AnyWidget itself defines a specification, not only for like the end
the people that author widgets, but also like what a host platform has to implement
in terms of APIs to support widgets.
So if you're using AnyWidget in a traditional Jupyter notebook, that protocol layer is like
the host platform, AnyWidget, the library, like plugs that in so that you can just load
them and like run in those environments.
But inside of Marimo, we actually like natively implement an AnyWidget API to like support
the AnyWidget protocol.
So there is no like Jupyter machinery inside of Marimo, but they do support AnyWidget.
So this thing that sort of started originally as a way for me to be able to author like
traditional Jupyter widgets, and now is like if you author them there, there are even more
platforms beyond Jupyter because if they can implement sort of the host side of that front
end code, now you have this contract where basically something's going to load this and
render these arguments.
And then you can expect these APIs to exist is basically the runtime contract.
It's been interesting to see too that a lot of tools like used to have these like catches,
like if I'm in Jupyter, do this.
If I'm in Colab, do this.
It's been interesting to see like a lot of big tools switch to just using AnyWidget like
that from that kind of like if else block of like what environment am I in?
But from what you're saying, Marimo also uses AnyWidget as kind of its native like widget
implementation, is that?
Yeah, if you want to make custom interactive elements, any Marimo has special machinery
to host AnyWidgets.
And then like the widgets themselves sort of have this internal state on the Python side
that is currently like based off of this library called traitlets.
That's just the Python side is like the AnyWidget or the machinery.
And what you can do is like pluck off individual pieces of state from those widgets to observe
as reactive values inside of your notebook.
So I'll declare my widget, I can use a decorator that's called like, it's like, or a function
is called mo.ui.AnyWidget and wrap my widget in that.
And that will just listen to every single value on that widget.
Or you can take individual pieces of state and lift them off of the widget as well.
And now you basically are like taking that internal reactivity and pulling those into
Marimo's reactive graph.
So now I can like reference a value in a different cell, and it plays nicely by Marimo's rules.
I'm curious too, I know you mentioned you've been working more lately on Marimo pair.
Maybe tell us a little bit about Marimo pair and the problem that solves.
Yeah, I'd say, you know, increasingly, we've started, I started using coding agents at
work for doing like traditional software development.
And we had like some initial sort of integrations with like coding agents for Marimo, but both
from our users and like my own personal experience, like there felt just kind of something off
when you tried to like do something in notebooks.
Like it was like, and I couldn't really put my thumb on it at the time, but it was just
like, okay, I have this data idea.
And, you know, with my coding agent, I can just let it loose in like a folder of a bunch
of script or on my file system and just like let it rip on a problem.
And I'll come back and I'll have a bunch of scripts and some outputs.
But like if I tried to use like integrations I'd tried with other types of notebooks, or
even with Marimo at that time, you'd like, the way that our integration worked then was
sort of, we'd edit the like the Python file on disk and try to like play the different
changes back inside the UI.
And what would happen is the, you know, you'd let the agent go and it would just kind of
say like, okay, good, I'm done.
Like it works.
And like, it like wasn't working.
There would be some like issue in the UI.
And then you really felt like you're kind of like babysitting this agent, which is like
a much different user experience to like working on traditional software where it's like, hey,
I have these tests, go run them until you like fix the problem.
Right.
Or like it's going to encounter syntax errors and like keep going until it like finishes
up.
So yeah, Marimo pair kind of spawned out of like taking a step back at how we were approaching,
like trying to drive, like use notebooks with agents.
And I really think our new framing of it is thinking about like notebooks, you know, notebooks
and stateful environments for coding have been useful for humans to understand data.
Is there a way that we can like actually make notebooks useful for agents as well for exploring
data problems?
And so it was not so much as like, can we use like a notebook as nice context for the
model, but like, can the model actually just use a notebook to like reason and like work
on a problem for a while?
And that, that changed, that led to us like really changing how we went about like exposing
our notebooks as a tool for agents.
Yeah.
I demoed Marimo pair for the company at like a work week because the fact that in Marimo,
it can just, the agent seems to be able to do anything, kind of like anything I could
imagine clicking.
It seems like the agent can do, I don't, there may be some limitations, but it's, it's been
so interesting to interact with.
Yeah, I'd say like previously, or the way that I'd read about using something like MCP
is like, it's, you know, model context protocol is this way of like taking an application
and like exposing it to like your agent.
And the way that we were using MCP before was kind of like allowing the agent to query
the state of the notebook.
So it'd be things like, you know, what are the cells?
What are the contents of the cells?
Edit, you know, what are my variables that are inside of the notebook?
But then what you, what we realized was like, you know, when the agent would take an action
like writing or mute, like doing something in the notebook, it was using its existing
tools to edit a file on disk, but it never got feedback for like, Hey, did something
go wrong?
Like in that same execution channel.
So it was kind of, so what the agent would have to get good at is like making a change
and then querying the notebook of like, and making a bunch of serial queries to be like,
did something go wrong?
And what we changed inside of Marimo pair is we basically got rid of like all of our
tools.
And we just have one tool that is like run Python code.
And that just runs Python code in the Marimo kernel.
And there's a hidden like Python API in there where the agent is able to control the Marimo
notebook and ask about the Marimo notebook itself.
And so when it does something like hallucinate a value or, you know, redefine a variable
or something that doesn't play nicely by Marimo's rules or Python's rules, it just gets feedback
in that same like turn that says, Hey, you need to change that.
Like that's not working.
There's an error.
And then it can keep going.
And that ability to, I think, have both that read only access and like see the effects
of the mutations, like a very similar way to like when you edit files on disk and then
run the scripts to see if they, you know, exit code one or zero.
Now the agent can do that at the cell level.
And that, I think, allows for this ability for, you know, the usefulness of notebooks
is that you can iterate very quickly.
And then when you try to like give agents to them previously, it started to feel like,
OK, but the agent isn't being very productive in this environment.
And I think that that was sort of the missing piece was like, how do you give them feedback
in that same execution channel to seeing, you know, what you're seeing so that you don't
have to sit there and tell it that something went wrong.
It is interesting that like data exploration is like so stateful.
When you think about like traditional software engineering, like you run your unit tests
and those are all designed in such a way that you start from a fresh session, they run and
you get the results back.
But like that just doesn't work for data analysis because it's so iterative.
And like, yeah, you want to be able to look at the state of the thing you just did and
you don't have to rerun the whole thing from scratch.
Every time we'll figure out some complicated like caching mechanism.
You just you want to have this like long running persistent session that records like what
have you done to the data?
It's interesting.
And one like interesting property, I think, of having a reactive kernel is that we don't
allow for these sort of so we don't allow for things where you like can, you know, inside
of if marimo pair, if the agent chooses to change a cell upstream, it will see the effects
of like the downstream cells of making that change.
So it sort of adds this extra layer of guardrails beyond just a normal Python REPL, or in order
for the agent to like continue on a problem, it has to check cells into the notebook and
define variables.
And then each of those cells has to play by marimo's rules.
So it's almost like, you know, yeah, traditional software development is very stateless, but
your state is kind of like your file system, right?
So you like version that over time, and then it's running these like scripts on top of
this state that you version over time.
And I think very similarly, we want to provide an experience like that in a stateful environment
with these guardrails around like, how you have to check those cells in.
So, you know, in marimo pair, you can't check in a cell that redefines a variable or something.
So it has to play nicely by marimo's rules.
And so sort of as a side effect of the agent exploring a problem using marimo, you get
like a reproducible kind of like execution flow.
There's a downside to that though, too, though, right?
Like, like what happens if like the thing at the end of the very end of the reactive
graph takes like a minute to run?
Like, how do you, like, I assume marimo must have like tools to like, when you don't want
things to run all the time to like opt out of opt out of that.
Yeah.
So the contract in marimo is that what you see on the screen is a representation of the
state in the kernel.
And so you can turn off reactivity or disable individual cells, and they will just show
as being stale.
And then you have to like manually execute them.
So if I turned on like lazy mode, then the agent would get feedback saying you need to
rerun these cells, but then it would, it could go back and run those cells.
It's interesting.
And what you're describing, I think for the agent, as I understand is marimo code mode.
Is that right?
The sort of secret backdoor into marimo that an agent can use to basically like create
cells or edit them.
And I think another thing you mentioned is like the connection to marimo that like, is
it right?
If, if the agent like deletes a cell that defined a variable, it's like the variable
itself is removed.
Is that, that's kind of part of the maintaining like a fresh state.
So it's like, in a way it kind of like locks in the agent into having like an up-to-date
environment.
And I don't know, I thought that was really intuitive that like, if I, as a human also
deleted a cell that defined the variable, I would also kind of want it to go away.
Like that's a really classic human blunder to like delete the ref, delete the code that
made it, but still have it like floating around in the environment.
That seemed like kind of a neat contract to enforce that if the code's gone, that, that
variable is gone as well.
Yeah.
Like it's, it's, it's a hidden Python API that the agent, like if you read the docs
inside of marimo, it's like, do not use this like yourself.
If you're a human being.
And part of that is that we, you know, we don't introduce in comparison to other APIs
that we have inside of marimo that we want people to like depend on like code mode was
something that we've like refined over time and we're still like changing.
And that's part of that is because like, because it's used within these sessions, the agent
learns about like what APIs it has available and how to call those in that session versus,
and that's a much different contract between like a model and like software versus like
two pieces of software where you have like versioning problems.
And like, you really have to make sure that they yeah.
Like if someone was building around code mode that was outside of using agents, like
they would get very annoyed with us when we made breaking changes versus the model basically
gets a new version of marimo and it has new capabilities or maybe we fix bugs and it just
calls those APIs and can sort of chug along inside the notebook.
Presumably code mode is what the marimo UI uses behind the scenes.
So most of marimo's UI is driven through like the front end, which is like JavaScript code.
So we've had a lot of like, you know, it's this message, I mean, to get technical, it's
like this message patching system of like edits, going back to the kernel, you have
some piece of state that you're updating.
But really we had to introduce like a Python API for driving marimo notebooks because,
which we didn't really have before.
And that made us changing a little bit about how our document model works.
So now you can like drive it from Python or you can drive it from the front end and they
can all like sort of share that state.
But you know, really the reason we were able to do that originally was just because our
kernel is in Python.
So when I first worked on marimo pair, the first thing introduced was just the ability
for the model to like run Python code in the kernel.
And that let it do basically everything that was like read-only inside of marimo.
So it's like, you know, we have this big set of MCP tools that were like list my data frame,
list my variables.
And now it's like, okay, get rid of all those.
You just write the Python code you want to like cat out a table, like print the columns,
like you can discover APIs, like just call Python the same way.
If you're running an agent and you see it using Python from the command line, it's like
running scripts like very quickly.
But then, and then I think the first thing I did was like, okay, show me a notification
in the UI.
And I saw it like, like try a bunch of different things.
And then finally it found like one API where it like toasted me a notification.
I was like, whoa, okay.
Like, how'd you do that?
And then like, we kind of like look back through the code.
And so we started to then think about like what types of things would you want to drive
from the kernel?
And then we harden those behind like a Python API that we could test and such that, you
know, you can have high confidence when the agent doesn't have to like get the right sequencing
of notifications.
It just calls an API.
And then we replay those notifications to the front end and also make sure the kernel
stays up to date.
Yeah, it's such an interesting approach.
And also I do think it's interesting to hear it in contrast to like the MCP or tools.
There's like a lot of ways to kind of carve this up.
But I think we've like broad, like in the early phases of like MCP being a thing, everyone
was like, let's make a bajillion MCP tools and then kind of discovered like, oh, actually
LLMs are like way better at writing code in an existing language than trying to figure
out some like bizarre novel set of tools that you have created.
And now like, I think, I mean, MCP still has a, as it plays a role, but it's so much more
powerful just to give it a few like tools that let it write code and do stuff like that's
really, really powerful.
Like we basically allow it to do, like, we still have a way of running Marimo pair through
MCP, but there's only one tool and it's like executing Python code.
And I think the other thing that was non-trivial to me that when we changed that way of having
many tools to like one very sharp tool is that programming languages have this, you
know, ability to like compose different primitives as well.
So like you don't have a bunch of different tool calls, you could actually in one execute
code.
It could like look at the notebook state.
It could like create multiple cells, delete cells.
Like if you don't have, those don't have to be individual transactions that you replay.
And instead it's like, you can leave it up to the creativity of the model to figure out
how to string these things together to accomplish the task that the user wants to do inside
the notebook.
Yeah.
I see that a lot when using Claude to write data analysis code, like it will write the
R code to ask, answer like three questions at once, rather than having to, yeah, like
ask us then, yeah, like what is the data?
What are the data frames?
What are the variables in the data frame?
What are their types?
Just does that all at one, one swoop and gives a bunch of information back to the model.
And I feel like just to set the stage too, for what, like when I use Marimo pair that
there's a skill, like essentially it was so interesting to be like,
okay, just use this skill.
I was using Claude code from the command line, just like plug it in and that Claude code
actually could, I mean, and this isn't a surprise, install Marimo, you know, essentially
fire it up on my computer, tab opens in my browser, and then just starts driving Marimo.
I feel like that was such a kind of eyeopening experience to realize like there's another
world where Marimo said like, Hey, set us up, you know, run the agent from inside Marimo
and it could do some stuff.
But to watch it actually like run, realize that we needed a blob on the outside, like
even running Marimo, opening it and orchestrating it, uh, was a really interesting experience
to, to see.
And the other thing I'll flag in, in correct me if I'm wrong, is that Claude code is
essentially using a CLI, like a bash tool.
Is that right?
To basically like ship this Python code in, this Marimo code mode in, to run in the kernel.
Is that, is that right?
Yeah.
So if you install the skill from like GitHub, which is the way that we recommend doing it,
you'll get a bash script that the agent can call that's called execute code.
And behind the scenes, what that does is it pings an API endpoint on Marimo that we have
set up that then replays or kind of maps the, that HTTP response back to your standard end,
standard out, um, standard error, and then exit with an exit code of zero and one.
Um, and what's cool about that is if, you know, so we have a cloud hosted version of
Marimo notebooks called Molab that runs like, um, where you have a kernel that's running in
the cloud.
And because it's all done over HTTP, you could actually point Marimo pair to like talk to a
remote version of, um, of your Marimo that's running.
And then you don't even need to have Marimo installed locally.
You just need curl and bash scripts.
So then you can be using cloud and like you're driving a remote notebook as well.
So in terms of like the distribution ergonomics, that has been like really nice in that
you can sort of like reduce the system dependency based off of like where people
want to be running the Marimo instance.
It's interesting.
Cause we, I think we, in some, yeah, cause you can also do the opposite, right?
You can provide a CLI, like you could have a Marimo CLI.
And if you call Marimo agent, then that produces the skill file that then that tells the agent
how to use it.
But you like you distribute the skill and then it gets that kind of CLI from that as
opposed to distributing the CLI and that gives the agent the skill.
Yeah, we've definitely found, I mean, part of it inside the Marimo UI, if you're on any
Marimo page, you can click in the top corner and then it says pair with an agent.
You can click in the top corner and then it says pair with an agent and we give you this little snippet that you can
run in your terminal that like sets it says use the Marimo pair skill and like, you know
Toast a notification and like here's where the notebook is running kind of thing
And that that is kind of the nicest experience I found to being able to launch it
It's just like you spin up Marimo then you click that and you can sort of be confident. You're connected and keep going
And that is kind of the nicest experience I found to being able to launch it, is just
like, you spin up Marimo, then you click that, and you can sort of be confident you're connected
and keep going.
But does that — like, how does that get the — how does that get the skill and the
bash script onto your computer?
Is that just like a curl command and then you SH it?
It's a subcommand in the Marimo CLI that, like, basically is like a prompt that says,
like, check to see if the — like, we check to see if you have the skill installed.
If you don't, then we'll, like, prompt Claude to, like, go get the skill and, like, have
you install it.
But if you ever — if you look at the Marimo pair skill, it also is, like, very uncoupled
to, like, the code mode internals.
Like, it basically tries to orient the agent around, like, the things that Michael was
talking about.
Like, you know, if a user's trying to do something with Marimo, like, what's a nice path forward
and, like, trying to help them, like, spin up Marimo.
And then the second piece is basically telling it, you have one tool, and then there's this
thing that's called code mode.
And, like, when you start a session, go look and see what code mode is in that instance
of Marimo that you have.
And so because we can ship changes to code mode, baking in, like, those API invocations
in the skill itself would kind of lead to this versioning problem.
And instead, what we've been able to do is, like, version the two independently, where
we just say, here's the skill, and then we can ship upgrades to Marimo, and we don't
have to worry about the two sort of, like, drifting from one another.
It is fascinating to me how agents can change the API ergonomics.
You know, like, one thing I think that's kind of interesting and surprising is, like, I
would say on average, like, agents are way better at reading error messages and actioning
them than humans.
So like, good error messages have always been important, but they're almost more important
now because you can assume that an agent will actually read it comprehensively, and
if you have a good suggestion, it will follow it.
And then that can make, like, APIs, like, way more discoverable on the fly, because
as long as the agent kind of gets somewhere in the vicinity, it then gets, like, pointed
to the right place.
Yeah, I'd say we've even thought now about, you know, as, like, when you're in a code
mode execution, having ways of streaming, like, agent-only logs or, like, suggestions
so that, like, a code path that goes down that, like, hey, you're probably, like, trying
to do this thing that doesn't really work, or, like, there's a better option.
Like, that's something we could, like, from Remo, say, actually use this API, and, like,
that, like, the agents do follow that really well, because you can sort of do this, like,
in-context learning almost of, yeah, actually do this instead, and as you were saying, they
follow it quite well.
Because the other interesting technique is to just implement the API that the LLM hallucinates,
which I think is also, like, a fascinating API design technique.
I would say that that was how, like, the early development of code mode was, because
I had sort of this idea of what I wanted that API to be, and then we ended up introducing
a skill, or I wrote a second skill that I called RetroPair, that would be if something
was, like, really annoying, or the agent stumbled a bunch, like, that skill basically looked
at the logs and tried to, like, diagnose, like, some stuff that was, like, kind of annoying
or, like, things that were hallucinated, and then we would have this, like, internal slack
where we just share around, like, hey, this happened, hey, this happened, and then that
was a nice starting point to refining the API for our team prior to us having, like,
better evals of, like, how code mode is being used.
Yeah, I love it.
I don't know.
It's so silly.
Like, I think a lot of people won't understand this, but I'm obsessed with code mode.
So I really appreciate you sharing.
I just feel like the design, there's something so reasonable and nice and composable.
It's such a, like, small set of choices, I feel like, but it's really cool to see how
they add up and basically, like, thread the needle between, like, what agents do well
and what people do well.
Yeah.
In fear of getting maybe, like, a little too technical on it, but it might be interesting
to this audience, part of the way that we implement code mode is within a async context
manager inside of Python.
So that's, like, if you ever use, like, with, you know, the with context manager with some
invocation of code as this other, you know, you get back this value variable that then
you can call with inside that block.
And what we actually do is that as the agents working, we don't actually perform any of
those operations within the code mode block itself.
They just are kind of, like, queued as a thing that the agent would like to do.
And then when it exits code mode, we kind of see if we can reduce, like, simplify that
invocation of code and replay it in such a way.
Or we can do things like we can check the code that the agent's going to run prior to
actually running it so that we can have high confidence that each transaction is, like,
okay, prior to, like, actually playing it back in the UI.
And so in terms of what Hadley was talking about, of giving this in context feedback,
if the agent tries to do some sequence of API calls that were like, whoa, you shouldn't
do that, we can actually just give it feedback that says you need to reverse or, like, change
something about the API call.
So we have this, like, little, like, level of indirection that allows us to inspect the
thing that the agent's trying to do and, like, view it as a holistic chunk and then try to
give some sort of verifiable checks that tell the agent, like, oh, no, don't do that or
do this.
You're like a SQL query planner, but for notebook updates, basically.
Much more simple.
Yeah.
So you said a lot about code mode and how, like, humans and agents can work together
or even agents can work really effectively with Marimo notebooks.
I'm really curious about the, from the other side, like, I saw that you all for a conference
wrote beyond the shell, like, this pitch for essentially, like, why should an agent go
beyond the shell?
Because a lot of us are using Cloud Code on the command line and a question might be from
the other side, like, why should Cloud Code choose Marimo to do data analysis rather than
running, like, Bash commands or Python scripts?
Could you say a little bit about that?
Like, what do agents get out of Marimo, would you say?
Yeah, that's a very fair and, like, good question.
So, and something we've been thinking about a lot, working on notebooks, right?
Like almost putting this existential question of, like, should we work on notebooks?
And I think similar to how, you know, we've got, like, humans have reached for tools,
like clearly notebooks or some sort of, like, live programming environment has been useful
for humans to work on data problems.
And I think we're, we're sort of continuing the pursuit that if we give the right ergonomics,
these can also be useful tools for agents to work on problems.
And part of that just comes from this, like, ability to iterate on the problem, right?
Like being able to, a lot of, like, data tasks involve this, I think, greater interplay at
times between, like, you know, the code you write and the inspection of the outputs and
then deciding what to do next.
Like, it can be a little bit more hands-on in the type of work that you're doing and
giving the agent the ability to, the environment that it's doing that work in, bring in the
human with, like, a very rich canvas, right?
Like, like you, Marimo, our notebook itself has the ability to embed these interactive
outputs or just even just plot, like, static plots, right?
Where different steps of that pipeline, the agent could say, like, hey, take a look at,
like, the data frame here, or I want to pause here and, like, go before I go on to the next
step.
So for, for one extent, I think it's a really interesting substrate for human, like the
notebook itself is a really interesting substrate for the humans and agents to sort of, like,
express together.
And the other is, I think, is really this idea of, like, you're sort of pushing the
models thinking into, into, like, code and having this, like, artifact that comes out
of that, like, session that you're working that resembles, like, what happened in that
discussion.
So, yeah, I was talking to the colleague about this recently, but, you know, if you, let's
say I have, like, a problem at work and I'm working with some data and, you know, it's,
I have, like, an instance of this problem where I open up my chat and I, like, start
working on my, I don't have any extra tools.
It's just the file system and maybe some Python and stuff.
I might solve that instance of that problem with, like, a directory of some scripts and
some outputs and a set of logs that describe, like, what that conversation was.
But the next instance of that problem, the starting point is maybe, like, I point at
that folder or I point at, like, and that conversation history from before.
And by, like, sort of forcing some standardization of, like, what that reasoning was and that
artifact that, like, came out of that session into something like a notebook, I think that
can be a really powerful way to, like, bootstrap, like, solving instances of those problems
in the future such that maybe you actually, you know, the next time you work on that type
of data task, you start in a notebook and maybe you, you work really hard on a notebook
that solves, like, a general version of that problem such that in the future, if you're
picking up sessions and it's just editing a couple cells to, like, get back to, like,
a very, like, similar type of output.
So I think by having this, you know, like, artifact from, like, these interactive sessions
with talking about data that do have the properties of code because it is code, like, that is
a really interesting property of, like, yeah, doing data work that is, like, more reusable
or sort of, like, a better starting point for some future work as well.
I'm still trying to wrap my mind around Cloud Code just picking up Marimo on its own.
Like, what do you, well, do you think there's a world where something like Cloud Code, even
if the human didn't get involved, like that, that something like Cloud Code would benefit
from Marimo, like, let's say I never read the output.
Do you think that there's a world where it would benefit from Marimo in that?
Yeah, well, so one thing is that these models, they've also been fine-tuned on, like, coding
tasks on, like, using the file system.
So they're really good at, like, grepping around and, like, looking for things.
But, like, that can kind of pollute context or, like, you can kind of, like, get context
very quickly if it needs to, like, scrub around to find, like, different values and things.
So I have some hunch that, you know, there's been some work previously in, like, using
Python REPLs with agents, but, like, you almost allow for the agent to put context
in variables or in memory, but then they can, like, choose to query back with code such
that, you know, instead of having to look at all the values of my data frame or skim
through a CSV, maybe, like, I'll just load that as a thing in memory that then I can
query multiple times more efficiently and get back, like, specific context.
So and then I think, again, like, if it's sort of like, what is the output of that work?
Maybe if it's just for, like, working on a data task where it's, like, one-off type
of thing, just letting Cloud Code rip, like, with Python and the file system, I think is
going to be totally fine.
But, you know, if, you know, we do have users using Marimo pair that, like, are, like, deploying
a lot of, like, headless versions of Marimo and that those all produce different Marimo
notebooks.
And then because it is that artifact, you can, like, spin up Marimo later and, like,
look at what the agent produced and compare them or, like, you have this sort of substrate
that then is more portable, or I can, you know, I don't have to necessarily give someone
my chat history and, like, a bunch of files and, like, a PDF.
I could, like, just give them the notebook that, like, the agent produced and pick up
from there.
I had another question related to, very closely related, like, a different interpretation
of Michael's question.
And that is, like, do you think at all about, like, how in the future, like, do you worry
people are just going to pop open Claude and be, like, analyze this data set?
And in that scenario, like, how, like, how do people, like, learn about Marimo?
Like, do you, do you start, like, you know, you obviously, you keep, like, previous thing
that we go to conferences, we'd, like, post on social media, like, that's how humans learn
about these tools.
Like, do we need to start thinking about, like, how do we tell Claude about our tools
so it uses them unprompted?
Yeah.
I think, I've been thinking about that a lot.
And I think also, like, Marimo itself is a very, like, code-first, like, user interface
for, like, working with data.
But, you know, in a happy future place, I would love it if somebody is popping open,
like, Claude desktop or Claude, you know, Codex desktop, and, like, they're asking questions
with data and behind the scenes, it's, like, using something like Marimo to, like, build
up some sort of, like, understanding with that data, such that, again, like, that user
is a much different user from someone like me that, like, knows how to write some code.
But, like, we're all sort of collaborating on a very similar, like, artifact, because
I do know folks, like, have friends that are less technical users, but have gotten interested
or feel very empowered in using, like, coding agents and coding tools.
And some of them will take, like, a PDF or something and, like, ask to, you know, have
some hunch about that data and want to ask a data question.
And then maybe it comes out with, like, a table, a markdown table in that chat that
says, like, here's, like, some answer, right?
And if you are presenting that to someone, the thing that you want to be able to answer
is that follow-up question of, like, how did you get to that number or where did that number
come from?
And I don't think a very, like, or I'm nervous about there being some world that we get into
where it's, like, well, here was my chat history that got me there, or, like, here was, like,
a set of scripts that ran and rather than, like, here's the code that made that sell
or, you know, something like Marimo, you could actually, if you ask a question of, you know,
where did that label for that access come from?
If you started that whole process in a Marimo notebook, you could actually trace that graph
all the way back to the beginning of, like, where that value changed and, like, change
that value there.
So I think having these artifacts that preserve that sort of, like, providence of that conversation,
but in code, whether or not you're looking at that code first, or maybe you're somebody
that's more a data practitioner that, yeah, is it, like, not a code, like, is it writing
code in their day to day?
But then the real existential question that you're asking Hadley is, like, how do you
get these tools into those environments?
And I don't know, is that buy in from, like, if it's something in enterprise where, like,
they're just equipped with these, right?
Like, like sort of coding tools out of the box, yeah.
And then how do you make sure, like, all of the, like, monetary benefits of that don't
accrue to, like, Anthropic and ChairGPT and, like, all of this open source support, all
this open source work just goes unsupported, yeah.
Like the, how, yeah, how are we going to complete that loop, like that feedback loop and all?
It's an interesting one, both, both asking, like, yeah, what, what will the tools use?
And, like, yeah, how, how will, like, open source software kind of be preserved and supported?
And also, I think to your point, like, how, yeah, well, how will organizations decide?
And we do kind of live in a world where someone could, like, vibe code a whole dashboard in
a myriad of ways, like, will there be benefits to building our dashboards in the same way,
say, in Marimo, so you can kind of crack it open and, and start from, like, a cell
or go back and look at the code and kind of see how things were made.
No, I'm, I'm a huge Marimo fan.
I feel like this style of notebook agents really, I, I liked notebooks before, but I,
I was open to the more R way of doing it, which is very text driven.
But I do feel like tools like Cloud Code and agents have really kind of reignited my love
of notebooks.
And I think in no small part due to like Marimo Codes interface.
So yeah, really appreciate you coming on.
I think it's so interesting to hear about the design, like, like just the human part,
you know, the design of the notebook, but also everything being done with this kind
of like agent human collaboration.
Yeah, super interesting stuff.
Really appreciate you coming on.
Any last notes or things you want people to know?
Try out Marimo Pair.
Yes.
I don't know.
I think.
It's just a skill away.
Right?
Yeah.
It is just one skill away.
I do think about the, you know, for a certain audience, like a skill is something that someone
understands and can install, but like, how do you like more broadly, as Hadley was saying,
like introduce the idea of that being like a way of shipping a piece of polished software
as well.
Yeah.
I, you know, when I started working at Marimo and before that working at any, working on
any widget, I think that my motivation around working on those tools was to try to eliminate
this like distance between like people and their data.
And I think that one thing I took for granted was that code, writing code has also been
like a barrier at times of like getting to that, decreasing that distance.
And so it, I'm, yeah, I'm personally very motivated to be in a place where my, my colleague
Vincent likes to say, like, we're not a, a no code platform or like a yes code platform.
And like, you know, humans can write code, agents can write code, and maybe that this
is like a really rich time to be playing around with, you know, the environment in which we
get closer to data and help make decisions with data.
Yeah.
That's awesome.
You know, really appreciate you coming on and yeah, for everyone, definitely highly
recommend Marimo Pair.
And I, I'll never say the old way again, Marimo for life.
So thanks.
Cool.
Thanks for having me on.
Thanks Trevor.
The Test Set is a production of PositPBC, an open source and enterprise tooling data
science software company.
This episode was produced in collaboration with creative studio Adji.
For more episodes, visit thetestset.co or find us on your favorite podcast platform.